and just as daenys foresaw the end of
valyria i go on foresaw the end of the
world of man just to begin with a
terrible winter
aegon called his dream the song of ice
and fire
Welcome back everyone it's Charlie this
will be my full house of the dragon
episode one video there's a whole bunch
of easter eggs for game of thrones a
bunch of new lore that they introduced
to the series so we'll break it all down
if you're brand new to the channel i'll
be doing videos for all the episodes be
sure to subscribe to get them all we're
doing a giveaway for hbo max
subscriptions all you have to do to
enter is be a subscriber and just post
your favorite moment from the episode on
the video careful for spoilers if you
haven't seen the episode yet we'll just
go through shot by shot talking about
easter eggs and w tough moments as we go
along some of the references were a
little more obvious than others like
they literally say a feast for crows in
a song of ice and fire during the
episode everybody pointing at the screen
saying oh my god they said the thing but
the title of the episode is heirs of the
dragon that's a reference to the fire
and blood book that they adapted for the
show it's like a targaryen history book
written as a history book is not written
like a song of ice and fire where each
chapter is written from each person's
perspective but heirs of the dragon is
like literally the title of a chapter
from fire and blood that details what
happened to all of aegon the conquerors
heirs and the targaryen kings that came
after him so when the show begins like
the actual present day of the show
viserys the first targaryen is the
fourth targaryen king of westeros the
voice over at the beginning of the
episode during the great council of
101ac is actually coming from the older
version of rainier targaryen though
which we won't meet till like halfway
through the series when they do a big
time jump the version of rainier that we
see in this episode is like the younger
version along with the younger version
of alicent for the most part though
everybody else on the show is playing
the younger and the older versions of
their characters but some people who
have seen that far ahead in the series
say that the time jump is relatively
seamless so it's not quite as weird as
it sounds when she talks about the first
century of the targaryen dynasty that's
just a reference to what's happened to
the realm since aegon conquered westeros
in the whole idea that leading up to
this event there were a lot of conflicts
like there was a lot of turmoil before
king jeharis became king but during
jiharis's reign like he's an old man
here during the past 50 years during his
reign there was this great period of
prosperity in the realm so it's kind of
like on the main show they talk about
all the stark children of the other
young characters being sweet summer
children because they know nothing of
winter like you were born during the
long summer everything has been great
while you've been alive later in the
episode you hear rhaenys joke about the
other young knights in the realm they
know nothing of real war they just meant
to foreshadow things eventually going
off the rails there are a couple battles
during this season but obviously the
real foreshadowing is for the eventual
dance of the dragons the targaryen civil
war that the show is really building up
to so the actual episode actually begins
with this quick flashback to the great
council of 101 ac it's at harrenhal and
notice how they got a big visual effects
upgrade like this is meant to be way
more book accurate than the version of
harrenhal that we saw during the main
show where king jahirus basically calls
all the lords of the realm to come have
a vote in who their next king is going
to be so that he can prevent a war they
pick viserys instead of rhaenys who had
been ahead of him in the line of
succession so rhaenys was the only
daughter of jihara's last surviving son
the previous heir who had died just
prior to this causing the big uproar
necessitating the great council jiharis
lived for a long time so he had many
children but most of them met either
untimely ends they were women or they
abdicated the throne at an early age
what ended up happening though is that
rhaenys became known as the queen who
never was because twice she was passed
over for the succession not just this
one time during the grand council this
was the second time it happened when her
father king jaharis's previous heir died
she was still in her mother's womb but
immediately upon learning of the death
jahirus passed over the unborn rhaenys
in favor of his younger son baelon
targaryen the only problem was is that
baelon also died an early death before
jiharis leading to the great council
here later rhaenys was named the queen
who never was by the court fool named
mushroom who a lot of the maesters went
to to chronicle the events of the
targaryen family history for fire and
blood there is no version of mushroom
that i could see during episode one i
don't know if they're going to do him as
a character during the series but it's
always possible fun fact we make a lot
of sister wiving and twin cess jokes
with game of thrones in house of the
dragon there's a lot of it happening
before your eyes in episode 1 here
really good example is viserys father
and mother were brother and sister
inside the line of succession so they
went full jaime and cersei but it was
actually king jaharis who legalized the
targaryens marrying each other within
the family that's why later when
daenerys and jon snow start getting it
on daenerys doesn't think that it's
weird like oh we've always done things
this way in my family but when we start
making all the sister-wiving jokes
obviously that led to the targaryen
madness developing because their genetic
pool just got worse and worse and worse
really good example of this manifesting
during the episode is viserys festering
wound on his back like he says that he
got cut by the iron throne which is also
a big easter egg in and of itself like
there's this belief in the realm that
the iron throne will basically reject
anyone who's not meant to sit on it so
the more you get cut by it the more
people will believe that you're not
meant to sit on it during the episode
viserys keeps talking about how he gets
cut by the iron throne at the end of the
episode he also gets cut again when he's
banishing damon targaryen but the funny
thing about this is that pretty much
anybody who sits on the iron throne gets
cut by it like it is the most stabby
cuddy throne that you've ever seen i'll
talk about it in a second too because
they got a huge visual upgrade like
obviously there are hundreds and
hundreds of swords here all over the
place as opposed to the version of the
iron throne we saw in the main series
there's a reason for that but the whole
idea here during the great council is
that rhaenys was voted down by all the
lords of the realm pretty much
unanimously which is why there wasn't a
war over the succession she just kind of
rolled with it because if she had
started a war it was basically going to
be her against the entire realm the
difference with the dance of the dragons
the targaryen civil war is that the
realm's allegiances were kind of split
down the middle during the last part of
the voiceover when the older rhaenyra
says that the only thing that can tear
down the house of the dragon is itself
she's also literally saying the name of
the show in her sentence here but the
voiceover is meant to foreshadow the
eventual dance of the dragons targaryen
civil war where literally it's targaryen
vs targaryen decimating their family
leading to the death of almost every
single one of their dragons only a few
dragons survived and most of their
family also died then the other major
change here is obviously to the actual
intro scene i don't know if this is
going to be the intro scene for all the
episodes or if it's going to be
different for episode two but obviously
it's almost like there is no intro scene
like how are we going to beat the game
of thrones intro scene because it was so
cool well we're not gonna do an intro
scene we'll win by not playing that game
hopefully this is just like a thing for
episode one and we'll get to like a more
normal intro when we get to episode two
most of the theme music is new but there
are a lot of songs and a lot of cues
that they use a lot of easter eggs for
music from the main series or a lot of
remixed music with themes from the
original series another huge change from
the original series is there's actual
text to sort of set you up for where
things begin in the timeline literally
mentioning daenerys targaryen in the mad
king what they're saying is that the
events of episode 1 largely take place
172 years before daenerys targaryen is
born and jaime lannister kills the mad
king her father during robert's
rebellion the actual events of game of
thrones episode 1 took place many years
after that then right after they
mentioned daenerys targaryen in that
intro scene they show rhaenyra writing
syrax in the sky huge visual scene
upgrade all the dragons all the special
effects because this huge upgrade but
they're playing some of daenerys
targaryen's theme music so they kind of
want you to think of this parallel
between daenerys targaryen and rainier
targaryen they are very different
characters like they have slightly
different personalities but they also
want to foreshadow that she's on a
similar path to daenerys like there's
this potential that she could either be
a really great figure or she could
eventually succumb to the targaryen
madness and meet a very very wtf
untimely end they try to give you a vibe
for her character just in general in the
first episode she's kind of like an arya
type of daenerys figure someone who's
very independent doesn't have a lot of
time for a lot of the courtly behavior
that people would expect of normal
highborne ladies as opposed to her best
friend during this period alicent
hightower who seems like she's all about
all this courtly behavior they give you
a quick tour of king's landing in
general like i said everything gets this
huge visual upgrade you see a version of
the dragon pit intact the version that
we saw in the main show had been
destroyed by that point of the timeline
it was actually built by king maegor
they referenced him a couple times in
the episode megor the cruel it was built
on the site of a former great sept after
the last great uprising of the faith
they show you some of the ways that
everyone views and treats dragons during
this period of the timeline they have
dragon handlers especially to take care
of them there the dragons respond only
to high valyrian commands because
obviously they come from ancient valyria
but as they say later in the episode
valerian the black dread is the only
living dragon or the only living thing
that actually survived from ancient
valeria pretty much all the other living
dragons that we see on the show were
born after the targaryens came to
dragonstone we meet graeme mctavish
who's playing harold westerling he's the
current lords commander of the
kingsguard we meet alicent hightower
like i said she's meant to be her best
friend during this period in the
timeline but obviously they're going to
show things slowly deteriorating because
alison hightower is the leader of the
greens the other faction in the dance of
the dragons rhaenyra being the leader of
the blacks that's why at the end of the
episode they show you her wearing green
literally just to kind of foreshadow
that eventual path previously alison was
also king jiharis's caregiver for his
final years so even though the high
towers in old town seem like this other
version of the tyrells she wears green
colors all the time kind of like the
tyrells her personality is nothing like
margery tyrell at least at this point
she's meant to be this very gentle very
nice person to everyone they take the
long way through the red keepers to give
you a quick tour of what the castle
looked like during the height of their
power when it was just really busy with
people being at court every day just
full of a small army of people all doing
very different types of things the room
they walk through here might also seem
familiar because it's the same room that
we see cersei later in the timeline
having the map of westeros painted on
during the main show if you pause the
episode while they're walking around the
castle and you kind of look around you
can see there are targaryen related
designs objects banners dragon related
everything all over the place what ended
up happening is that when robert
baratheon took the iron throne he
basically had anything targaryen related
removed from the red keep that's why a
lot of the dragon skulls that were
inside the throne room were moved down
below is also one of the reasons why
there aren't like a hundred swords
around the iron throne because when
robert baratheon took over he got rid of
a lot of those swords but for this show
they wanted to do a much more book
accurate version of the iron throne but
it's still sort of a compromise because
the actual book accurate iron throne
looks like this it's massive and there's
just no practical way they could
actually film that in these scenes but
the funny thing you may have noticed
here too when they're showing the iron
throne is that because they needed so
many swords they wanted to have a couple
easter eggs in the background so there
are swords from warcraft and the witcher
melted into this version of the iron
throne let me know if you actually spot
them in the episode we meet rainier's
mother viserys first wife emma aaron she
was a targaryen on her mother's side
king jiharis was also her grandfather so
for example viserys didn't sister wife
but he did marry his cousin
during the episode she talks about
having many many miscarriages and
stillbirths probably had something to do
with all of the sister wiving going on
in that family also there's a really
dark easter egg in her death during the
episode her mother also died birthing
her in a similar way her mother died
from sickness so she wasn't cut open but
she still died giving birth to her the
same way that emma died giving birth to
baelon they used this scene to kind of
give you an idea for the way ranira
views herself during this part of the
timeline the way that other people view
her like nobody thinks of her as a
potential candidate for the iron throne
at this point they all just kind of
expect her to have the life that normal
highborne ladies have like someday we're
going to marry you off to one of the
other powerful lords in the realm and
you're going to have a bunch of children
by him and most people are expecting
viserys to eventually have a son and for
the son to take the iron throne or for
his brother damon to take the iron
throne during the small council meeting
corlys velaryon mentions the triarchy
crab eater beginning to become a problem
down in the stepstones that's
foreshadowing for all the big battle
scenes we see in the trailers they will
definitely become a huge problem
culminating in the actual battle of the
stepstones but that won't happen until
way later this season the reason he's
called crab feeder is because he ties up
his victims in low tide so when the tide
comes in literal crabs will come and eat
them that's why you see all these crabs
crawling around here on the beach he is
literally feeding the crabs a lot of
these small council meeting scenes are
also meant to give you a vibe for king
viserys frane people generally view him
as a weak king just because he wasn't
really a fan of making the hard choices
that you expect kings to be able to make
he didn't want to choose his successor
to like the last possible second he
doesn't want to worry about the
potential threat of the triarchy he's
more concerned with his son's birth and
with the great tournament here he's
meant to be similar to robert baratheon
in that sense like remember during game
of thrones season one there was a big
tournament that's all robert cared about
even though it was bankrupting them so
you have a couple people who just were
not meant to actually be king when you
see rhaenyra has been serving as this cup
bearer this has been going on for a long
time he actually raised her at court
here learning all the things that you
would need to learn as the next world so
she was actually raised getting like the
best tutorial and how to be a good queen
as possible so the whole idea is there
hadn't been a battle for the succession
and she had become queen she actually
might have been a pretty good queen when
they mentioned damon targaryen in the
city watch he's the person who created
the gold cloaks like there was always a
city watch but he turned them into the
gold cloaks that's why in the main show
they call them the gold cloaks going
around the horn here lord beesbury is
the master of coin corlys velaryon is
the master of ships rhys ifans is
playing otto hightower he's the hand of
the king his older brother is lord
hightower who we meet at the end of the
episode ruling over the family seat in
old town
melos is the current grand maester and
lionel strong here is the master of laws
and i love the way they introduce you to
matt smith's damon targaryen character
for the first time with him sitting on
the iron throne which is like a huge
no-no like you can get in really big
trouble for doing stuff like that but
his nickname in westeros is the rogue
prince like he is the black sheep of the
family who wants nothing to do with the
normal rules of court he wants to become
king like he lets it be known to many
people in the episode that he expects to
become king and he believes that the
targaryens have become complacent and he
wants to take their family back to what
they were like during aegon's conquest
so that's one of the reasons why the
others in the small council are worried
about what he might do if he were to
become king like he could potentially
become another make or the cruel but
even though he does a lot of wtf things
during the episode they want to show you
that he isn't mad like megor the cruel
was like he's hardcore but he's not
crazy they give you a brief idea for
what their relationship is like like
rainier and damon both talk high
valyrian to each other like their own
special language even though all the
targaryens technically speak high
valerian some of the only things that
damon actually cares about in the world
are his dragon caraxies who we meet
during the episode and rhaenyra herself
they have this weird flirtatious
chemistry going on between the two of
them but he's about 12 years older and
she's actually really young at this
point in the timeline so it actually
takes a while before they go full jamie
and cersei but things are like slowly
heading in that direction we see rainier
and alicent in the godswood of king's
landing under the heart tree with a face
carved into it there is a god's wood in
king's landing you just don't see it
during the events of the main series
they're reading the story about nymeria
and the 10 000 ships that's kind of an
easter egg for them actually doing a
version of the show on hbo eventually
like they're actually developing a
version of a nymeria show but in this
scene she's also meant to be an example
of a very independent woman like rhaenyra
wants to become kind of like an arya
daenerys type of situation
when she talks about seeing the wonders
across the narrow sea she's talking
about essos we do see a little bit of
essos later in the series because of
what's happening with the triarchy also
this whole lesson that they have here
about nymeria heading to dorne being
pursued by the ancient valerians is
meant to be a reference to the fact that
in present day of the seven kingdoms
aegon the conqueror and the subsequent
targaryen kings up to this point haven't
been able to conquer dorne so right now
technically it's still the six kingdoms
in dorne they also set up a lot of
foreshadowing with king viserys
character with his festering wound from
the iron throne like i said it's meant
to be important of his ill health and
it's just going to continue to get worse
and worse and worse through the show
he's kind of like a sean bean type of
character in that way kind of like a ned
stark like oh he's clearly going to be a
main character then all of a sudden the
rug gets pulled out from under you like
up goodbye because the actual targaryen
civil war the dance of the dragons is
the battle for the iron throne it can't
actually begin until there is no one
sitting on the iron throne so he has to
die before it can start so this is like
this big ticking clock for his character
so don't be surprised if you see more
scenes where he's like wow this wound is
getting a little bit worse suddenly i
have this weird persistent cough they
make a reference to aima not bathing in
hot water which is meant to be a mirror
for daenerys in game of thrones episode
1 taking the scalding hot bath not being
burnt by fire because dragons cannot be
burnt by fire
they mentioned vicinia and vegard the
visenya they're referencing is aegon the
conqueror's sister wife visenya and
vegar is the current oldest living
dragon on the show because blair in the
black dread has died recently
viserys talks about the dragon dreams
that he had of his son baelon similar to
daenerys visions but just like daenerys
the twist here is that viserys is also
kind of misinterpreting what the visions
mean when he says he heard all the
sounds of battle and all the dragons
roaring is one he was probably actually
seeing the coming targaryen civil war
with everyone's dragons fighting each
other and when he says he places their
son on the iron throne eventually they
do place one of viserys's sons on the
iron throne but not the sun that he
thinks it's going to be then we actually
meet damon targaryen's new gold cloaks
versus the city watch and have this huge
wtf montage of them just killing as many
criminals as they can get their swords
on
like i said it's meant to be evidence
that the people in the small council use
that damon will eventually become a very
cruel king like maegor but also when
he's justifying his actions he's not
wrong like damon says we have all these
nobles coming viserys even backs him up
saying oh yes ever since grandmother
died king's landing has gotten worse and
worse and worse the grandmother he's
talking about is king jaharis's wife
queen alisan
probably the most wtf scene here though
is the dude getting his junk cut off so
rip it just reminds you of what ramsay
bolton did to theon greyjoy so pour one
out for them the other thing that's
going on here too this part of the city
is near flea bottom they also call damon
targaryen the lord of flea bottom so
he's like the most hated and most
beloved person on westeros at the same
time so like half the people really hate
him and the other half really love him
but the other big connection to him
being called the lord of flea bottom
here is because we see him in so many
brothels near this area later in the
episode there's a couple scenes to sort
of set up the dynamic between him and
the rest of the small council like
obviously otto hightower really does not
like him but the whole idea is that otto
hightower isn't meant to be like another
version of littlefinger or even like
tywin lannister but they both hate each
other with a fiery passion when damon
makes a joke about his wife rhea royce
she lives up near the veil that's where
he gets banished to by viserys at the
end of the episode the reason why he
doesn't really care about her is because
it's a marriage that was forced on him
like a lot of highborne people get
marriages forced on them just to form
alliances that had nothing to do with
them loving the other person speaking of
lovers we meet mysterio for the first
time she's gonna be a pretty big
character during the series her nickname
given to her by the people around her is
misery she's kind of like a version of
littlefinger varys and melisandre all
mixed together she eventually becomes
mistress of whispers to rainier
targaryen and just continues to be
daemon's lover they finally have the
heirs tournament is a vastly upgraded
version of the tournament that we saw in
game of thrones season one a lot of
familiar moments here like they show you
a lot of different great houses they try
to show you a much bigger version of
what a great tournament would look like
but mostly this is here to introduce the
criston cole character he's born the
steward of the current lord danderian
which will make you remember barrick
dindarian from the main show he's kind
of like a mixture of brienne of tarth
with jaime lannister like he really
wants to become a knight do all these
good things become a member of the
kingsguard like brienne does but winds
up getting mixed up in a lot of really
really spicy stuff classic jamie
lannister style they also want to show
you that he's a much better fighter than
damon targaryen which is saying a lot
like damon is meant to be one of the
best fighters in westeros so when
criston cole puts him on his ass it's a
huge deal
you also notice damon targaryen takes
the opportunity to slight otto hightower
as much as possible by taking out his
oldest son and asking for his daughter
alicent's favor i think his dragon scale
armor looks way better in the actual
episode than it did in all the promos
they released for the episode it's meant
to look very similar to the type of
armor that rhaegar wore during robert's
rebellion zoom in enhance you also
notice during this scene that viserys is
wearing the cat's paws of hilarion
dagger on him he wears it at all times
really it's the same dagger that
littlefinger used to start the war of
the five kings later in the timeline and
then that arya used to kill the night
king and for those asking yes there are
more valyrian swords like damon uses a
valerian sword called dark sister that
you see here he uses it a bunch of times
during the episode viserys wields
blackfyre aegon the conquerors former
sword that they passed down to each new
targaryen king there are more valerian
weapons flying around during this period
of the timeline some of them have not
been lost yet so like longclaw for
instance is still with house mormon so
the handle will still be designed to
look like a bear instead of like a
direwolf but when damon targaryen gives
the valerion necklace to rainier it's
still meant to be super rare like it's
incredibly incredibly expensive and then
they have a huge wtf montage with them
inner cutting the death of viserys wife
and his son with damon losing to criston
cole it is just meant to foreshadow the
beginning of the end for their family
like nothing is certain all the good
times that they experience under king
jiharis's rule are over for the most
part things are just going to continue
to get darker and darker and darker like
easy come easy go the burial scene here
even though it's very somber is meant to
be kind of a mirror for daenerys using
drogon to burn samwell's father and
brother like they buried all the
targaryens dead like this it was part of
their customs too and this also ties
back to aegon the conquerors prophecy of
a song of ice and fire the whole long
night burning your debt like
incinerating your dead because if you
leave someone's skeleton intact they can
just be raised as a white later as we
saw during later seasons like oh that's
why they burn their dead when they're
discussing the succession viserys
literally says a feast for crows which
is the title of book 4 of a song of ice
and fire and then when otto hightower
sends his daughter alicent to
quote-unquote comfort viserys it's also
kind of the beginning of their
relationship alison in viserys's he's in
the middle of making a replica model of
the ancient valyrian freehold hopefully
we'll see some flashbacks to that or
some more depictions of it and as he
says he's a huge history nerd he loves
reading the history text about ancient
valyrians the ring he's holding here
though what he's crying is his wife's
wedding ring that was given to her when
they were married the fact that she's
wearing the green dress is also meant to
foreshadow her eventually representing
the greens faction in the targaryen
civil war but there's not really that
much sinister stuff going on here like
otto hightower wasn't throwing her at
viserys or anything like he generally
thinks that he's doing what's right for
the realm right for the king and just in
general being good at his job issues
that slowly over time they spend more
and more time together eventually they
develop a relationship the demon
basically gets exiled to the veil for
insulting viserys dead son baelon and as
you can see it actually play out he was
mournful of them like he wasn't trying
to mock his dead cousin otto hightower
was just giving the information to
viserys out of context because obviously
he kind of hates damon and he doesn't
really care about him that much so damon
wasn't trying to insult baelon in this
moment it's just another example of
damon's big mouth getting him in trouble
like he still shouldn't have said it but
he didn't mean it the way that viserys
thinks that he meant it as they're
yelling at each other here he's holding
blackfyre one of the big things is that
later in the timeline eventually the
sword does get lost after the blackfire
rebellions and as damon leaves you can
see viserys get cut by the iron throne
again like i said another ill portent of
things to come then the scene of him
naming ranira as his heir happens in the
monument that they erected to belier in
the black dread his real skull after his
death valerion died when he was about
200 years old that's how he got so big
basically viserys was his last writer
but he only rode him one time so like
this whole scene here especially when
they start talking about aegon the
ancient valerions the song of ice and
fire the long night the night king the
white walkers it's just meant to be
loaded with meaning in general when he
talks about the doom of valeria he
implies that the valyrians caused the
doom because of their greatness and
their hubris thinking that they could
control dragons and thinking themselves
gods above everything else when really a
lot of people think that the doom was
caused by a lot of over mining around
the 14 flames the area of volcanoes and
that's what caused them to all go off
blowing up this entire area of the
continent they intercut the lords of the
realm swearing filthy to her in front of
viserys while he also reveals aegon's
prophecy of the long night literally
saying that aegon the conqueror's real
reason for conquering the seven kingdoms
was to unite the realm and create a
force to face the night king of the
white walkers because of a dragon dream
that he had like i said dragon dreams
are kind of like visions of the future
that they have but a lot of people can
misinterpret them in aegon literally
called his dream a song of ice and fire
the name of the entire book series when
he tells renir that this is a secret
that's passed from targaryen king to
each targaryen king the way george r
martin clarified it is that when aegon
had the dream and tried to unite the
seven kingdoms thinking about the long
night nobody actually knew when it was
going to happen so each new targaryen
king when they learned about it and kind
of took up the mission as their own
thought that it was right around the
corner nobody knew it was going to be
almost 200 years before it actually
happened but also part of the idea here
is that had the dance of the dragons not
happen and like had they not killed off
half their family and most of their
dragons the realm probably would have
been much better equipped to fight the
night king in the white walkers damon
then takes his dragon caraxes and
miseria back to the veil that's probably
not gonna stick for that long and just
after he tells her the prophecy of a
song of ice and fire they end the
episode with her facing camera in the
theme song from the main show plays
called a song of ice and fire like the
actual song is named a song of ice and
fire it played in the very last episode
of game of thrones in the outro but if
you spotted any other big easter eggs or
references in the episode that i didn't
mention in the video be sure to write
them in the comments my episode 2
trailer video will post next in my full
house of the dragon episode 2 video will
post next week after they release it
everyone click here for the new trailer
i'll update the link as soon as i post
that and click here to learn all about
the special kind of magic that dragons have
thank you so much for watching
everyone stay safe and i'll see you guys in the next one!